<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Posts on Antimatters</title>
		<link>//florin.antimaterie.ro/en/posts/</link>
		<description>Recent content in Posts on Antimatters</description>
		<generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
		<language>en-us</language>
		<lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
		<atom:link href="//florin.antimaterie.ro/en/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
		<item>
			<title>Relația cu politica</title>
			<link>//florin.antimaterie.ro/en/posts/politics/</link>
			<pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>//florin.antimaterie.ro/en/posts/politics/</guid>
			<description><![CDATA[%!s(<nil>)]]></description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="asta-e-o-pagină-de-test">Asta e o pagină de test.</h1>
<ul>
<li>
<h3 id="să-zicem-că-avem-un-text-mai-lung-indentat">Să zicem că avem un text mai lung (indentat):</h3>
<ul>
<li>Matthew Tabone, care a început să lucreze la Parlamentul European pentru Metsola în 2013, îi succede Leticiei Zuleta De Reales Ansaldo. Aceasta preia un nou rol, de director al relaţiilor cu parlamentele naţionale în Parlamentul European, citează News.ro.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Dar și un bloc nou. Poți pune direct public::true și pagina devine publică</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Smolin&#39;s &#34;Einstein&#39;s Unfinished Revolution Zettels&#34;</title>
			<link>//florin.antimaterie.ro/en/posts/smolins-einsteins-unfinished-revolution-zettels/</link>
			<pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>//florin.antimaterie.ro/en/posts/smolins-einsteins-unfinished-revolution-zettels/</guid>
			<description><![CDATA[%!s(<nil>)]]></description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>date:: 26-08-2024
title:: <strong>Bohr&rsquo;s complementarity principle as a form of kantian neo-idealism</strong>
tags:: idealism, cuantică, realitate, quantum theory, reality
folgezettel:: {2r1}
status:: draft
category:: Zettelkasten</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Bohr&rsquo;s position is reminiscent of Kant&rsquo;s inaccessibility of the &ldquo;object in itself&rdquo;. We cannot access the ultimate nature of quantum objects but can only construct representations of them. And what we observe is the response of our instruments, never the object itself. #To investigate: the question of neo-Kantianism in modern quantum.</p>
</li>
<li>
<blockquote>
<p>@Einstein&rsquo;s unfinished revolution: the search for what lies beyond the quantum <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, <sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup></p>
</blockquote>
</li>
<li></li>
<li></li>
<li>
<hr>
</li>
<li>
<ul>
<li>parent</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<hr>
</li>
<li>
<ul>
<li>I think this note relates to this other note.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>date:: 26-08-2024
title:: <strong>A theory is a description of reality, one that defines a possible image of that reality by providing snapshots of it. It is not a model of reality</strong>
tags:: reality, measurement, quantum theory
folgezettel:: {2th1}
status:: draft
category:: Zettelkasten</p>
<ul>
<li>While we postulate a unique reality, apart from our measurement and observation, we can only access and describe part of it. A scientific theory is a discourse about the reality, equivalent to a natural language description but using a mathematical language, able to provide a model for predictions. If the theory provides good predictions, in tune with experimental measurements, we say it&rsquo;s a true theory. But we fail to realise that we create &ldquo;a snapshot&rdquo; of reality by observing it. While most theories can describe time evolution, their basic truths are time-independent, description of instants.</li>
</ul>
<p>What the theory analizes are these snapshots, and not the reality; i.e. the results of our measurements, not the objects we measure. We then extrapolate the variables to the objects themselves (like mass, speed etc) and try to predict their evolution.</p>
<p>In this sense it is only natural that what we call &ldquo;wave function&rdquo; collapses when we measure the quantum object. The data we gather is like a picture on a photographic plate, a snapshot of the situation as our instruments can &ldquo;see it&rdquo;, it&rsquo;s not actually what the observed object was doing. The wave function is not an intrinsic property of the quantum object, but an extrinsic theoretical property. (Think &ldquo;Entropy&rdquo;, this is not something our senses can directly perceive, nor something producing direct effects for our senses. It&rsquo;s an extrinsic theoretical property)</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>There is also the observation (below) made by Smolin that quantum states are the information we have about the system, not the physical system.</p>
</li>
<li>
<blockquote>
<p>@Einstein&rsquo;s unfinished revolution: the search for what lies beyond the quantum<sup id="fnref1:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p>
</blockquote>
</li>
<li></li>
<li>
<hr>
</li>
<li>
<ul>
<li>parent</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<hr>
</li>
<li>
<ul>
<li>I think this note relates to this other note.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p><em>“Bohr called the new philosophy complementarity. Here is how he talked about it: Neither particles nor waves are attributes of nature. They are no more than ideas in our minds, which we impose on the natural world. They are useful as intuitive pictures that we construct from observing large-scale objects such as marbles and water waves. Electrons are neither. Electrons are microscopic entities that we cannot observe directly, and so we have no intuition about them. To study electrons we must construct big experimental devices to interact with them. What we observe is never the electron itself; it is only the responses of our big experimental devices to the tiny, invisible electrons.” P. 135</em>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref1:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p><em>“Bohr talked about the complementarity between life and physics, between energy and causation, and, indeed, between knowledge and wisdom.” P. 136</em>&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>ZETTEL DRAFTS</title>
			<link>//florin.antimaterie.ro/en/posts/zettel-drafts/</link>
			<pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>//florin.antimaterie.ro/en/posts/zettel-drafts/</guid>
			<description><![CDATA[%!s(<nil>)]]></description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[]]></content>
		</item>
		
		<item>
			<title>Appearance and Reality</title>
			<link>//florin.antimaterie.ro/en/posts/appearance-and-reality/</link>
			<pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
			
			<guid>//florin.antimaterie.ro/en/posts/appearance-and-reality/</guid>
			<description><![CDATA[%!s(<nil>)]]></description>
			<content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Attachments</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="zotero://select/library/items/97RCH3WY">Appearance and Reality.pdf</a> {{zotero-imported-file 97RCH3WY, &ldquo;Appearance and Reality.pdf&rdquo;}}</li>
</ul>
<p>Notes</p>
<ul>
<li>
<h1 id="una-din-problemele-care-rezultă-din-teoria-asociativă-e-aceea-că-un-obiect-nu-e-definit-decât-de-asocierile-lui">Una din problemele care rezultă din teoria asociativă e aceea că un obiect nu e definit decât de asocierile lui.</h1>
</li>
</ul>
<p>În cazul ăsta obiectul în sine dispare, nu e decât un “slot” conceptual, ceea ce-l definește e ceea cu ce e în relație.</p>
<p>Definiția e în fond asta, a inventaria conceptele cu care definitul e în relație permanentă. Dacă vizualizăm această relație între concepte ca o rețea, atunci putem spune că un nod e practic un punct fără dimensiune care e definit de nodurile cu care e legat. E practic o intersecție de proprietăți. Dacă elimini legăturile nu mai rămâne nimic! Zahărul, fără proprietățile lui nu mai e nimic.</p>
<p>Dar, zice Bradley:</p>
<p>„And we are forced to see, when we reflect, that a relation standing alongside of its terms is a delusion.. If it is to be real, it must be so somehow at the expense of the terms, or, at least, must be some thing which appears in them or to which they belong.” (Bradley, 1893, p. 35)</p>
<p>În definiția unui nod de rețea ceea ce contează nu e nodul ci relațiile lui cu alte noduri. Când spunem “zahărul e dulce, alb, tare” definim de fapt relațiile nodului “zahăr” cu celelalte noduri.</p>
<p>A fi înseamnă de fapt a avea relații bine determinate cu alte concepte.</p>
<p>Problemele par a apare din cauză că confundăm felul în care conceptele obiectelor sunt în relație cu conceptele proprietăților lor cu felul în care obiectul în sine e în relație cu lumea. Dar cuvântul “zahăr” e altceva decât bucata de materie albă de pe masă. Cu alte cuvinte existența obiectului în lume e una în timp ce existența conceptului între celelalte concepte e altceva.</p>
<p>Însă noi nu putem experimenta lumea altfel decât ca sumă de fenomene abstractizate în conștiință</p>
<ul>
<li>
<h1 id="discuție-despre-rostul-și-rolul-filosofiei">Discuție despre rostul și rolul filosofiei</h1>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Într-o discuție cu Victoria a apărut ideea că rolul filosofiei e terapeutic. Ceea ce vrea să vindece e acel “mal de vivre” franțuzesc.</p>
<p>Pentru asta, mijloacele ei nu sunt exclusiv argumentul; esențială e prezența “maestrului”. În jurul lui Socrate oamenii se strângeau ca în jurul lui Jean, atrași aparent de “discuții” dar în realitate de liniștea pe care o întrezăreau în acest mod de a analiza și trăi viața.</p>
<p>Cât despre cui se adresează, în mod limpede chestiunea nu are legătură cu pregătirea și cultura individuală. Petrică cu 4 clase a putut înțelege de la Jean Mitul Peșterii și s-a putut minuna autentic de noua lui înțelegere. Probabil că “accesul” la înțelepciunea filosofiei se poate defini așa: dacă îți pui întrebări și ai neliniști, e pentru tine. Dacă nu, nu. “Bate și ți se va deschide”.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<h1 id="deosebirea-între-calitățile-primare-și-secundare-e-greșită-nu-există-decât-calități-secundare">Deosebirea între calitățile  primare și secundare e greșită. Nu există decât calități secundare.</h1>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Atât cuantica cât și relativitatea dărâmă mitul proprietăților absolute ale unui obiect (care nu depind în nici un fel de observator). În cuantică simpla observare alterează mărimile măsurate, iar ceea ce măsurăm nu poate fi decât ulterior rezultatului măsurării, nu există o valoare absolută precedentă. În relativitate atât poziția cât și dimensiunea dar și timpul, depind de relația între sistemul observatorului și cel al obiectului, adică nu toată lumea vede acelaă lucru. Cu alte cuvinte există doar calități secundare, nu și primare.</p>
<p>Această stare de fapt trimite către ideea că atunci când observăm lumea noi suntem cei care îi atribuim “calitățile” iar mecanismul prin care facem asta e unul de proiecție.</p>
<p>(cu consecința ultimă că toate mărimile fizice sunt proiecții și nu calități ale obiectelor. E ceea ce Sellars și McDowell sugerează indirect - vezi mai jos)</p>
<p>Bradley argumentează de fapt că extenia, luată ca o calitate primară, depinde de fapt de simțuri, deci nu e primară.</p>
<p>„The extended comes to us only by relation to an organ ;” (Bradley, 1893, p. 28)</p>
<h2 id="filosofi-care-au-atins-și-sugerat-mecanismul-de-proiecție-ca-instrument-cognitiv-fundamental">Filosofi care au atins și sugerat mecanismul de proiecție ca instrument cognitiv fundamental:</h2>
<p>CGPT:</p>
<p>One philosopher who wrote explicitly about the non-existence of primary qualities, often engaging indirectly with F.H. Bradley&rsquo;s metaphysical views, is <strong>Wilfrid Sellars</strong>.</p>
<ul>
<li>Wilfrid Sellars was significantly influenced by the historical context of British Idealism, and while his philosophy diverges in many respects, he addresses some of the same issues about perception and reality that F.H. Bradley dealt with, particularly the non-existence of independently existing primary qualities.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="sellars-conceptual-framework">Sellars&rsquo; Conceptual Framework</h3>
<p><strong>Relevant Work:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>In his seminal work, <em>&ldquo;Empiricism and the Philosophy of Mind&rdquo;</em> (1956), Sellars challenges the traditional distinction between primary and secondary qualities, arguing that all qualities are ultimately bound by the conceptual framework within which they are perceived and understood.<strong>Core Argument:</strong></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Sellars critiques the foundational empiricist idea that sensory experience can provide a direct access to &ldquo;primary qualities&rdquo; independently of &ldquo;secondary qualities.&rdquo; He argues that all sensory experiences are theory-laden and mediated by our conceptual apparatus, thus there are no purely objective primary qualities distinct from our perception and interpretation.<strong>Example Notion:</strong></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Sellars&rsquo; famous dictum, “the myth of the given,” posits that nothing is given in experience in an unmediated fashion. This idea fundamentally undermines the notion that primary qualities exist independently of conceptualization and perception, aligning with the critique that Bradley and others implied about the relational nature of all perceived qualities [1].</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="related-philosophical-contributions">Related Philosophical Contributions</h3>
<p><strong>John McDowell:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>John McDowell, a contemporary philosopher influenced by Sellars, further elaborates on these themes in works such as <em>&ldquo;Mind and World&rdquo;</em> (1994). McDowell argues that our perceptual experience is always already shaped by our cognitive faculties, thus reinforcing the idea that there are no purely objective primary qualities.<strong>Illustrative Argument:</strong></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>McDowell builds on Sellars and Kantian themes to argue that the so-called primary qualities are conceptually structured; there is no perceptual access to a &ldquo;raw&rdquo; reality outside of our interpretative frameworks [2].</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="summary-of-key-points-on-the-non-existence-of-primary-qualities">Summary of Key Points on the Non-Existence of Primary Qualities</h3>
<p>Sellars&rsquo; and McDowell&rsquo;s arguments underscore a pivotal shift in the philosophy of mind and epistemology:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Conceptual Mediation:</strong> All sensory experiences are mediated by conceptual understanding, thereby dissolving the strict division between primary and secondary qualities.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Myth of the Given:</strong> Sellars&rsquo; critique of the idea that primary qualities can be directly apprehended without interpretative context reveals that primary qualities, as traditionally conceived, do not exist in an independent, objective sense.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Perception and Reality:</strong> Both philosophers highlight that what we perceive (whether considered primary or secondary qualities) is always a product of the interplay between sensory data and our conceptual schemes.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>Wilfrid Sellars, through his critique of the &ldquo;myth of the given,&rdquo; argues directly against the existence of primary qualities as independent of perception and conceptual understanding. This line of thought has been influential in contemporary philosophy, with thinkers like John McDowell further developing these ideas, effectively questioning the classical distinction between primary and secondary qualities in the process.</p>
<h2 id="problema-obiectivității-și-măsurabilității-calităților-primare">Problema obiectivității și măsurabilității calităților primare</h2>
<p>ChatGPT:</p>
<p>You&rsquo;ve raised an insightful point, and indeed, the advent of theories in modern physics like relativity and quantum mechanics has fundamentally challenged the classical distinction between primary and secondary qualities. Let&rsquo;s explore this in more depth:</p>
<h3 id="relativity-and-the-concept-of-primary-qualities">Relativity and the Concept of Primary Qualities</h3>
<p><strong>Theory of Relativity:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Albert Einstein&rsquo;s theory of relativity (both special and general) has shown that measurements of space and time are not absolute but relative to the observer&rsquo;s frame of reference. This implies that primary qualities such as spatial extension (shape, length) and motion are not fixed and can vary depending on the observer&rsquo;s velocity and gravitational context.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Example:</strong> An object&rsquo;s length can appear contracted (Lorentz contraction) to an observer moving at high speed relative to the object. Thus, there&rsquo;s no single, absolute measurement of length that can be said to be the object&rsquo;s &ldquo;true&rdquo; length.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="quantum-mechanics-and-observer-effect">Quantum Mechanics and Observer Effect</h3>
<p><strong>Quantum Mechanics:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>In quantum mechanics, the observer effect highlights that the act of measurement itself affects the system being observed. Moreover, properties like position and momentum are described by probability distributions rather than definite values until measured.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Example:</strong> The famous Heisenberg Uncertainty Principle states that you cannot simultaneously know the exact position and momentum of a particle. This indeterminacy challenges the classical notion that primary qualities of particles are fixed properties that exist independently of observation.<strong>Wave-Particle Duality:</strong></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>Quantum entities exhibit both wave-like and particle-like properties. Whether an entity is measured as a wave or a particle can depend on the type of measurement apparatus used, further emphasizing that its primary qualities aren&rsquo;t inherent but context-dependent.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Example:</strong> Electrons can display interference patterns (a wave property) under certain experimental conditions, and particle-like impacts under others, depending on how the experiment is conducted.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="implications-for-primary-vs-secondary-qualities">Implications for Primary vs. Secondary Qualities</h3>
<p>Given these revolutionary insights from modern physics, the previous distinctions and certain assumptions about primary qualities become much more complex:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Observer-Dependence:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Both relativity and quantum mechanics suggest that primary qualities such as size, shape, and motion are not absolute properties but can change based on the observer&rsquo;s frame of reference or interaction.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Interconnected Nature of Qualities:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The fluid nature of quantum phenomena implies that what we might have considered secondary qualities (dependent on perception) and primary qualities (independent of perception) are deeply interconnected.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Contextual Reality:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The understanding of properties as contextually determined rather than universally fixed aligns more closely with the nature of secondary qualities historically described in philosophy.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="revisiting-the-distinction">Revisiting the Distinction</h3>
<p>The relativistic and quantum paradigms compel us to revisit and likely revise our philosophical categorizations:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>No Absolute Primary Qualities:</strong> The idea that primary qualities exist independently and absolutely is increasingly untenable. Instead, all qualities might be seen as relational and context-dependent, diminishing the strict boundary between primary and secondary qualities.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Holistic Perspective:</strong> A holistic perspective recognizes that properties (whether traditionally seen as primary or secondary) are deeply interwoven with the conditions of observation and measurement.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="reflections-in-philosophy">Reflections in Philosophy</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Phenomenology and Existentialism:</strong> Philosophers like Edmund Husserl and Maurice Merleau-Ponty have emphasized the role of human perception and experience in defining reality, resonating with the idea that all qualities are interdependent and relational.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h1 id="introducere">INTRODUCERE</h1>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="rolul-metafizicii">Rolul Metafizicii</h2>
<p>„Is it possible to abstain from thought about the universe ? I do not mean merely that to every one the whole body of things must come in the gross, whether consciously or unconsciously, in a certain way. I mean that, by various causes, even the average man is compelled to wonder and to reflect.” (Bradley, 1893, p. 17)</p>
<p>Impulsul de a reflecta la originea și sensul lumii e general uman, nu specific filosofilor. (ce se ascunde în spatele a ceea ce văd, ce prdine, ce rațiune ascunsă) Argumentul lui Bradley e că dat fiind acest interes, e important să înțelegem cum putem reflecta cel mai bine la problemele astea, iar ăsta e rolul metafizcii:</p>
<p>„Metaphysics takes its stand on this side of human nature, this desire to think about and comprehend reality. And it merely asserts that, if the attempt is to be made, it should be done as thoroughly as our nature permits.” (Bradley, 1893, p. 18)</p>
<h2 id="de-ce-continuăm-cu-metafizica-din-moment-ce-ea-nu-produce-răspunsuri-valabile">De ce continuăm cu metafizica din moment ce ea nu produce răspunsuri valabile?</h2>
<p>În principiu pentru că e singura ale de mijloc între aboprdarea religioasă și cea materialistă.</p>
<p>„There is, so far as I can see, no other certain way of protecting ourselves against dogmatic super- / stition. Our orthodox theology on the one side, and our common-place materialism on the other side (it is natural to take these as prominent instances), vanish like ghosts before the daylight of free scepti cal enquiry.” (Bradley, 1893, p. 19)</p>
<h2 id="metafizica-e-calea-intelectuală-către-dumnezeu">Metafizica e calea intelectuală către Dumnezeu</h2>
<p>„And, with certain persons, the intellectual effort to under stand the universe is a principal way of thus ex periencing the Deity.” (Bradley, 1893, p. 19)</p>
<p>date:: 1893
publisher:: MACMILLAN
title:: @Appearance and Reality
item-type:: book
original-title:: Appearance and Reality
language:: en
authors:: F.H. Bradley
library-catalog:: Zotero
links:: <a href="zotero://select/library/items/5MHAQRYT">Local library</a>, <a href="https://www.zotero.org/users/7453955/items/5MHAQRYT">Web library</a></p>
<p>Attachments</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="zotero://select/library/items/97RCH3WY">Appearance and Reality.pdf</a> {{zotero-imported-file 97RCH3WY, &ldquo;Appearance and Reality.pdf&rdquo;}}</li>
</ul>
<p>Notes</p>
<ul>
<li>
<h1 id="una-din-problemele-care-rezultă-din-teoria-asociativă-e-aceea-că-un-obiect-nu-e-definit-decât-de-asocierile-lui-1">Una din problemele care rezultă din teoria asociativă e aceea că un obiect nu e definit decât de asocierile lui.</h1>
</li>
</ul>
<p>În cazul ăsta obiectul în sine dispare, nu e decât un “slot” conceptual, ceea ce-l definește e ceea cu ce e în relație.</p>
<p>Definiția e în fond asta, a inventaria conceptele cu care definitul e în relație permanentă. Dacă vizualizăm această relație între concepte ca o rețea, atunci putem spune că un nod e practic un punct fără dimensiune care e definit de nodurile cu care e legat. E practic o intersecție de proprietăți. Dacă elimini legăturile nu mai rămâne nimic! Zahărul, fără proprietățile lui nu mai e nimic.</p>
<p>Dar, zice Bradley:</p>
<p>„And we are forced to see, when we reflect, that a relation standing alongside of its terms is a delusion.. If it is to be real, it must be so somehow at the expense of the terms, or, at least, must be some thing which appears in them or to which they belong.” (Bradley, 1893, p. 35)</p>
<p>În definiția unui nod de rețea ceea ce contează nu e nodul ci relațiile lui cu alte noduri. Când spunem “zahărul e dulce, alb, tare” definim de fapt relațiile nodului “zahăr” cu celelalte noduri.</p>
<p>A fi înseamnă de fapt a avea relații bine determinate cu alte concepte.</p>
<p>Problemele par a apare din cauză că confundăm felul în care conceptele obiectelor sunt în relație cu conceptele proprietăților lor cu felul în care obiectul în sine e în relație cu lumea. Dar cuvântul “zahăr” e altceva decât bucata de materie albă de pe masă. Cu alte cuvinte existența obiectului în lume e una în timp ce existența conceptului între celelalte concepte e altceva.</p>
<p>Însă noi nu putem experimenta lumea altfel decât ca sumă de fenomene abstractizate în conștiință</p>
<ul>
<li>
<h1 id="discuție-despre-rostul-și-rolul-filosofiei-1">Discuție despre rostul și rolul filosofiei</h1>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Într-o discuție cu Victoria a apărut ideea că rolul filosofiei e terapeutic. Ceea ce vrea să vindece e acel “mal de vivre” franțuzesc.</p>
<p>Pentru asta, mijloacele ei nu sunt exclusiv argumentul; esențială e prezența “maestrului”. În jurul lui Socrate oamenii se strângeau ca în jurul lui Jean, atrași aparent de “discuții” dar în realitate de liniștea pe care o întrezăreau în acest mod de a analiza și trăi viața.</p>
<p>Cât despre cui se adresează, în mod limpede chestiunea nu are legătură cu pregătirea și cultura individuală. Petrică cu 4 clase a putut înțelege de la Jean Mitul Peșterii și s-a putut minuna autentic de noua lui înțelegere. Probabil că “accesul” la înțelepciunea filosofiei se poate defini așa: dacă îți pui întrebări și ai neliniști, e pentru tine. Dacă nu, nu. “Bate și ți se va deschide”.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<h1 id="deosebirea-între-calitățile-primare-și-secundare-e-greșită-nu-există-decât-calități-secundare-1">Deosebirea între calitățile  primare și secundare e greșită. Nu există decât calități secundare.</h1>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Atât cuantica cât și relativitatea dărâmă mitul proprietăților absolute ale unui obiect (care nu depind în nici un fel de observator). În cuantică simpla observare alterează mărimile măsurate, iar ceea ce măsurăm nu poate fi decât ulterior rezultatului măsurării, nu există o valoare absolută precedentă. În relativitate atât poziția cât și dimensiunea dar și timpul, depind de relația între sistemul observatorului și cel al obiectului, adică nu toată lumea vede acelaă lucru. Cu alte cuvinte există doar calități secundare, nu și primare.</p>
<p>Această stare de fapt trimite către ideea că atunci când observăm lumea noi suntem cei care îi atribuim “calitățile” iar mecanismul prin care facem asta e unul de proiecție.</p>
<p>(cu consecința ultimă că toate mărimile fizice sunt proiecții și nu calități ale obiectelor. E ceea ce Sellars și McDowell sugerează indirect - vezi mai jos)</p>
<p>Bradley argumentează de fapt că extenia, luată ca o calitate primară, depinde de fapt de simțuri, deci nu e primară.</p>
<p>„The extended comes to us only by relation to an organ ;” (Bradley, 1893, p. 28)</p>
<h2 id="filosofi-care-au-atins-și-sugerat-mecanismul-de-proiecție-ca-instrument-cognitiv-fundamental-1">Filosofi care au atins și sugerat mecanismul de proiecție ca instrument cognitiv fundamental:</h2>
<p>CGPT:</p>
<p>One philosopher who wrote explicitly about the non-existence of primary qualities, often engaging indirectly with F.H. Bradley&rsquo;s metaphysical views, is <strong>Wilfrid Sellars</strong>.</p>
<ul>
<li>Wilfrid Sellars was significantly influenced by the historical context of British Idealism, and while his philosophy diverges in many respects, he addresses some of the same issues about perception and reality that F.H. Bradley dealt with, particularly the non-existence of independently existing primary qualities.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="sellars-conceptual-framework-1">Sellars&rsquo; Conceptual Framework</h3>
<p><strong>Relevant Work:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>In his seminal work, <em>&ldquo;Empiricism and the Philosophy of Mind&rdquo;</em> (1956), Sellars challenges the traditional distinction between primary and secondary qualities, arguing that all qualities are ultimately bound by the conceptual framework within which they are perceived and understood.<strong>Core Argument:</strong></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Sellars critiques the foundational empiricist idea that sensory experience can provide a direct access to &ldquo;primary qualities&rdquo; independently of &ldquo;secondary qualities.&rdquo; He argues that all sensory experiences are theory-laden and mediated by our conceptual apparatus, thus there are no purely objective primary qualities distinct from our perception and interpretation.<strong>Example Notion:</strong></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Sellars&rsquo; famous dictum, “the myth of the given,” posits that nothing is given in experience in an unmediated fashion. This idea fundamentally undermines the notion that primary qualities exist independently of conceptualization and perception, aligning with the critique that Bradley and others implied about the relational nature of all perceived qualities [1].</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="related-philosophical-contributions-1">Related Philosophical Contributions</h3>
<p><strong>John McDowell:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>John McDowell, a contemporary philosopher influenced by Sellars, further elaborates on these themes in works such as <em>&ldquo;Mind and World&rdquo;</em> (1994). McDowell argues that our perceptual experience is always already shaped by our cognitive faculties, thus reinforcing the idea that there are no purely objective primary qualities.<strong>Illustrative Argument:</strong></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>McDowell builds on Sellars and Kantian themes to argue that the so-called primary qualities are conceptually structured; there is no perceptual access to a &ldquo;raw&rdquo; reality outside of our interpretative frameworks [2].</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="summary-of-key-points-on-the-non-existence-of-primary-qualities-1">Summary of Key Points on the Non-Existence of Primary Qualities</h3>
<p>Sellars&rsquo; and McDowell&rsquo;s arguments underscore a pivotal shift in the philosophy of mind and epistemology:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Conceptual Mediation:</strong> All sensory experiences are mediated by conceptual understanding, thereby dissolving the strict division between primary and secondary qualities.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Myth of the Given:</strong> Sellars&rsquo; critique of the idea that primary qualities can be directly apprehended without interpretative context reveals that primary qualities, as traditionally conceived, do not exist in an independent, objective sense.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Perception and Reality:</strong> Both philosophers highlight that what we perceive (whether considered primary or secondary qualities) is always a product of the interplay between sensory data and our conceptual schemes.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="conclusion-1">Conclusion</h3>
<p>Wilfrid Sellars, through his critique of the &ldquo;myth of the given,&rdquo; argues directly against the existence of primary qualities as independent of perception and conceptual understanding. This line of thought has been influential in contemporary philosophy, with thinkers like John McDowell further developing these ideas, effectively questioning the classical distinction between primary and secondary qualities in the process.</p>
<h2 id="problema-obiectivității-și-măsurabilității-calităților-primare-1">Problema obiectivității și măsurabilității calităților primare</h2>
<p>ChatGPT:</p>
<p>You&rsquo;ve raised an insightful point, and indeed, the advent of theories in modern physics like relativity and quantum mechanics has fundamentally challenged the classical distinction between primary and secondary qualities. Let&rsquo;s explore this in more depth:</p>
<h3 id="relativity-and-the-concept-of-primary-qualities-1">Relativity and the Concept of Primary Qualities</h3>
<p><strong>Theory of Relativity:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Albert Einstein&rsquo;s theory of relativity (both special and general) has shown that measurements of space and time are not absolute but relative to the observer&rsquo;s frame of reference. This implies that primary qualities such as spatial extension (shape, length) and motion are not fixed and can vary depending on the observer&rsquo;s velocity and gravitational context.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Example:</strong> An object&rsquo;s length can appear contracted (Lorentz contraction) to an observer moving at high speed relative to the object. Thus, there&rsquo;s no single, absolute measurement of length that can be said to be the object&rsquo;s &ldquo;true&rdquo; length.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="quantum-mechanics-and-observer-effect-1">Quantum Mechanics and Observer Effect</h3>
<p><strong>Quantum Mechanics:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>In quantum mechanics, the observer effect highlights that the act of measurement itself affects the system being observed. Moreover, properties like position and momentum are described by probability distributions rather than definite values until measured.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Example:</strong> The famous Heisenberg Uncertainty Principle states that you cannot simultaneously know the exact position and momentum of a particle. This indeterminacy challenges the classical notion that primary qualities of particles are fixed properties that exist independently of observation.<strong>Wave-Particle Duality:</strong></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p>Quantum entities exhibit both wave-like and particle-like properties. Whether an entity is measured as a wave or a particle can depend on the type of measurement apparatus used, further emphasizing that its primary qualities aren&rsquo;t inherent but context-dependent.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Example:</strong> Electrons can display interference patterns (a wave property) under certain experimental conditions, and particle-like impacts under others, depending on how the experiment is conducted.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="implications-for-primary-vs-secondary-qualities-1">Implications for Primary vs. Secondary Qualities</h3>
<p>Given these revolutionary insights from modern physics, the previous distinctions and certain assumptions about primary qualities become much more complex:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Observer-Dependence:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Both relativity and quantum mechanics suggest that primary qualities such as size, shape, and motion are not absolute properties but can change based on the observer&rsquo;s frame of reference or interaction.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Interconnected Nature of Qualities:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The fluid nature of quantum phenomena implies that what we might have considered secondary qualities (dependent on perception) and primary qualities (independent of perception) are deeply interconnected.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Contextual Reality:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The understanding of properties as contextually determined rather than universally fixed aligns more closely with the nature of secondary qualities historically described in philosophy.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="revisiting-the-distinction-1">Revisiting the Distinction</h3>
<p>The relativistic and quantum paradigms compel us to revisit and likely revise our philosophical categorizations:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>No Absolute Primary Qualities:</strong> The idea that primary qualities exist independently and absolutely is increasingly untenable. Instead, all qualities might be seen as relational and context-dependent, diminishing the strict boundary between primary and secondary qualities.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Holistic Perspective:</strong> A holistic perspective recognizes that properties (whether traditionally seen as primary or secondary) are deeply interwoven with the conditions of observation and measurement.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="reflections-in-philosophy-1">Reflections in Philosophy</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Phenomenology and Existentialism:</strong> Philosophers like Edmund Husserl and Maurice Merleau-Ponty have emphasized the role of human perception and experience in defining reality, resonating with the idea that all qualities are interdependent and relational.</p>
</li>
<li>
<h1 id="introducere-1">INTRODUCERE</h1>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="rolul-metafizicii-1">Rolul Metafizicii</h2>
<p>„Is it possible to abstain from thought about the universe ? I do not mean merely that to every one the whole body of things must come in the gross, whether consciously or unconsciously, in a certain way. I mean that, by various causes, even the average man is compelled to wonder and to reflect.” (Bradley, 1893, p. 17)</p>
<p>Impulsul de a reflecta la originea și sensul lumii e general uman, nu specific filosofilor. (ce se ascunde în spatele a ceea ce văd, ce prdine, ce rațiune ascunsă) Argumentul lui Bradley e că dat fiind acest interes, e important să înțelegem cum putem reflecta cel mai bine la problemele astea, iar ăsta e rolul metafizcii:</p>
<p>„Metaphysics takes its stand on this side of human nature, this desire to think about and comprehend reality. And it merely asserts that, if the attempt is to be made, it should be done as thoroughly as our nature permits.” (Bradley, 1893, p. 18)</p>
<h2 id="de-ce-continuăm-cu-metafizica-din-moment-ce-ea-nu-produce-răspunsuri-valabile-1">De ce continuăm cu metafizica din moment ce ea nu produce răspunsuri valabile?</h2>
<p>În principiu pentru că e singura ale de mijloc între aboprdarea religioasă și cea materialistă.</p>
<p>„There is, so far as I can see, no other certain way of protecting ourselves against dogmatic super- / stition. Our orthodox theology on the one side, and our common-place materialism on the other side (it is natural to take these as prominent instances), vanish like ghosts before the daylight of free scepti cal enquiry.” (Bradley, 1893, p. 19)</p>
<h2 id="metafizica-e-calea-intelectuală-către-dumnezeu-1">Metafizica e calea intelectuală către Dumnezeu</h2>
<p>„And, with certain persons, the intellectual effort to under stand the universe is a principal way of thus ex periencing the Deity.” (Bradley, 1893, p. 19)</p>
]]></content>
		</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
